[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so contemplating cessation, let's call it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, nirodha is usually translated as cessation, so...
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't really matter how you translate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it doesn't matter as much as how you contemplate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how would you contemplate cessation?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you contemplate nirodha?
[SPEAKER_02]: On a day-to-day practical basis, what would that contemplation entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are there ways in which I'm acting by body or by speech or by mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, say, say you're not, you're restrained, you're not acting out, you're not perpetuating the ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how would you then go about contemplating nirodha in aggregates, in feelings, perceptions, intentions, consciousness?
[SPEAKER_02]: What, what actual property
[SPEAKER_02]: What actual quality would you be reflecting upon if you're contemplating nirodha of the aggregates?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it you're contemplating their disappearance?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's kind of inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, while you're alive, while you're paired with, you know...
[SPEAKER_02]: While these aggregates are composed the way they are, you couldn't even conceive them not being there, because your thought of their cessation is within the existing aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about aggregates disappearing from your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about your feelings not arising, or your perceptions never coming back again, and intentions just going numb.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about that, because that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is it about then?
[SPEAKER_01]: To see that they have arisen on their own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have come.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are there, and then... What would be the quality of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Say, you're currently doing feeling, or perception, or your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what would be the quality?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would be the quality of, eh... nirodha in those things?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would be the quality of that, eh... that, eh... arisen on its own, unknowable?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the nirodha in that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not about cessation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about disappearance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about this perception should disappear for me in order to understand it will be free from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Freedom from besetting perceptions, freedom from painful feelings, freedom from pressures, is while those things are present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, when the nirodha is translated as cessation,
[SPEAKER_02]: That cessation does... well, should not be understood in the sense of these things just not being there anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cessation not being the disappearance, what is it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Disappearance of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandonment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Disappearance of ownership, yeah, you could say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because that thing would still remain, but you would not own it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, yeah, like you're saying,
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, would you say that contemplating nirodha in aggregates is contemplating non-ownership of the aggregates?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you could say that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any other way you could contemplate those aspects?
[SPEAKER_02]: They would contribute towards the contemplation of non-ownership?
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be contemplating rightly along the lines of nirodha, along the lines of cessation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Along the lines of unknowability, because it kind of boils down to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't own it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like your own feelings, your own moods, your own perceptions, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, the only way to like thoroughly understand the extent of that non-ownership, you have to allow that thing to arise to its full extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: To whatever extent it wants to arise, you must not be interfering with its arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the Sotāpanna's understanding is, whatever has the nature of arising, that's why it's nirodha, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it has a nature to cease, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: to be unownable, to be seen as completely, pretty much impossible to own in any shape or form while it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, the mere arising of things, the mere arising of your feelings, of your intentions, of your perceptions, is then showing you its own unknown ability.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, the mere arising then starts equaling freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you allow it to the extent... if you allow it to rise to the extent it wants to rise, to that extent you'll be free from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, you will not be hindered, obstructed by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, you will not take up the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: But kind of seeing arising as a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, when I say arising, means manifestation, means enduring, means finding it there, means coming into being, intensifying, fading in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter how you want to describe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't mean like...
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same senses, eh... nirodha does not mean the ending.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arising does not mean you see its beginning before which it was not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because then that's... Because, yeah, if you're observing something that it was not and now it just appeared, that's not on the right level where the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's too particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's just something secondary within your sense bases that you are just measuring, like scientists and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, we're talking about on the level of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you, as an observing individual, are not
[SPEAKER_02]: Absorbed in observation, but actually, emphasis is on the self-reflection of the experience of observation, or whatever else you might be doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: On that level, you find things already being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pressuring you, being felt, being intended, being perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, recognizing their manifested enduring there, without acting out, obviously.
[SPEAKER_02]: To the extent that it's manifested, to that extent you become free.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because no extent can be owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason you never get to understand that, fully, is because you interfere with the extent of arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it's pleasant, you cut it short by wanting more of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's unpleasant, you cut it short by trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's neutral, you cut it short by ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't actually get to see the obvious, which is whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature to cease for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has the nature to not hinder you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has the nature to not be owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has the nature to be impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Has the nature of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like we said many times, it's... it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the beginning as well, because you act because you are affected by it, and then, through acting, you affirm your ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: The right instruction has to come from the outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody who has understood this has to tell you, and you have to take it out of faith, initially, just so that you stop acting out and cutting it short.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by the way, there are many, like, day-to-day examples of how you would cut short these mental states.
[SPEAKER_02]: Psychologization would be one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Explaining things, because they bother you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, so you get some resolution, you want to deal with those things on that level, mental level, to clarify, to free yourself from doubt, through finding answers and all of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: All that's rooted in cutting the unpleasant feeling short.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, somebody says, oh, see, now all this thinking is just causing you suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just observe sensations, watch the nostrils, and do not allow thoughts, basically, to arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's another way of cutting things short.
[SPEAKER_02]: You, again, you don't want to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, one way you want to deal with it too much, this way you don't want to deal with it at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if it has arisen, to the extent it has arisen, to that extent you have to endure it, because that's the only way to fully, kind of,
[SPEAKER_02]: Hammer in the fact that it's unownable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you might be telling yourself that it's unownable as much as you want, but when unpleasant feeling manifests itself, when something that bothers you comes up, and you just want to resolve it, deal with it, ignore it, turn away from it, meditate away from it, means you took the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you're acting out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it's unownable, what is there to resolve, if it's not yours?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is there to be bothered about and deal with it and fight over?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the difference between theory and the practice, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, everybody can read anicca and can say, oh, this is anicca, that's anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: But do you, when the pressuring things manifest, do you allow them to arise to the extent they want to arise?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you able to remain composed in your samādhi without acting out of them for as long as they last?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the measure of whether you are actually seeing that nirodha correctly or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you're getting closer to see it correctly or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you are extinguishing the ownership or fueling it through acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could another way of describing this contemplation be
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's not, it's never in the content of, you know, unpleasant experiences or pleasant experiences or neutral experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's always the attitude towards those feelings or those experiences.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in the broadest sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the reason why that would, for most people, especially in the beginning, that might be just too abstract for them, like when you say feeling in the broader sense, it just becomes an abstract category that they cannot relate to, is because the body and the actions have not been purified and the mind has not been withdrawn from unwholesome states through sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you're still operating on the level of content of your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasing content, displeasing content, you know, prolong, avoid, gain more.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the sheer kind of broadness of the category of feeling, in that broader sense of a mood, pleasant, unpleasant, neutral, that's just too far to be seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just an abstract thought that has no practical relevance, because the mind has not been elevated to that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you elevate it, not through a special practice or a magical method or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: You elevate it through saying no to your desires.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're gonna start going up, which is why, you know, people get scared.